Ragnar!
Odin!
Come on. Let's go home.
Watch.
What are you two doing?
I'm taking Bjorn to
the thing tomorrow.
Not yet. He's not old enough.
He's 12 years old.
Take him next year.
Next year is soon enough.
He'll need a silk
ribbon. Lagertha.
You're a handsome boy.
Funny ears. though.
Don't sleep with lots
of women in Kattegat.
I can do without
it for a few days.
Is that another way
of saying you love me?
Huh?
I always dream of you.
Last night. I dreamt you were
feeding me blood pudding.
What does that mean?
It means you're
giving me your heart.
Get your dog. boy.
Frodi! Come on. boy.
What will happen at the thing?
The Earl will deal with
some criminal offenses.
and then. we'll discuss
the summer raids.
And where will you go?
The Earl decides.
He owns the ships.
He'll send us to the east.
as always. to the Baltic lands.
but I want to know
what's to the west.
What cities and
gods are over there.
See. I'm not satisfied
with this.
Odin gave his eye
to acquire knowledge.
but I would give far more.
And will Earl Haraldson let you?
Good.
Like this. nice and tight.
And on three.
One. two. three.
Very good. Gyda.
Gyda. feed the goats.
Go on!
What do you want?
We know you're all alone here.
All the men are gone.
If you're thirsty. I
will give you a drink.
If you're hungry.
I will feed you.
Otherwise. you must go.
We will eat and drink after
we've satisfied our other needs.
I don't want to kill you. woman.
You couldn't kill me if
you tried for 100 years.
Out!
I went to confess
my love to her.
but I was set upon by a bear
and an enormous hound
who guarded her home.
I killed the bear with my spear.
and I managed to strangle
the hound with my bare hands.
And that is how I gained
her hand in marriage.
Did she tell you the same story?
Just about.
Are you ready to receive your
arm ring and become a man?
Yes.
And what does a man do?
He fights.
And?
He looks after his family.
That's right.
Could you look after our family?
What do you mean?
You look after us.
Say I wasn't there.
I have a big decision to make.
It may change many things.
Now. go to sleep. You
have a big day tomorrow.
Bjorn!
So. here you are. brother.
Rollo.
By Freyr and all the
gods. how you've grown.
Hello. Rollo.
Are you here for the thing?
You're a real man now.
Come. let's get a drink.
Looking a little pale. Bjorn.
Why don't you go lie down?
So where do you think the Earl
is going to send us this year?
Those bastards to the
east are as poor as we are.
I know.
That's why we should sail west.
I've heard such tales. Rollo.
Great towns and
cities and treasures.
Hoards of gold and
silver. and a new god.
I've heard those stories.
too. but what does it mean?
We can't sail across
an open ocean.
I believe there's
a way to go west.
I have something that
will change everything.
What?
What is that? Now just listen.
A while back. I met someone.
a wanderer.
He told me it was
possible to go west.
over the open sea.
using this.
It's a sun board.
It needs to sit in water.
Another wanderer?
This time. it's different.
Now tell me. Ragnar.
this wanderer of yours.
has he ever sailed west himself?
Just get some water.
Now. this candle is the sun.
Every day. the sun rises
up into the sky until noon.
See how the shadow shortens?
At noon. it is at its shortest.
That only tells me how
far south I have traveled.
Didn't I just tell
you to listen?
The day before sailing. you
mark a circle around the pointer
where the shadow is
at its shortest at noon.
The next day at sea.
you place the board back
into water around noon
and watch the shadow.
If the shadow only
touches the circle...
Your course remains true?
Yes.
And if it passes outside
the circle. like this...
Then you have drifted. and
you must steer further south.
Yes.
And what if it never
reaches the circle?
Then you are too far south.
and must steer more to the north.
That's it!
Keep the noon
shadow on the circle.
and your course will be true.
West.
But what if there is no sun?
How can the board help you then?
How could you find your way?
Using this.
Follow me outside.
They call it a sunstone.
You see?
There is the sun.
Now we go west.
Come on. Come on.
Silence!
Olaf Anwend. you have pleaded
guilty to the charge of stealing.
Tomorrow. you will
run a gauntlet of stones
and turf as punishment.
Yes. Lord. Thank you. Lord.
Let it be known.
a fine is to be paid
by anyone who fails
to throw something.
Bring in the next accused.
There he is! - Murderer!
Burn him!
Eric Trygvasson. you
are accused of the murder
of Sigvald Strut this January.
How do you plead?
It wasn't murder. Lord. I
killed him in self-defense.
Liar!
If it wasn't murder.
why did you not
declare your crime
to the first person that
you met afterwards.
as the law obliges?
In fact. you passed by several
houses before you reported it.
I thought the relatives of the
dead man might be living in them.
The law allows you to pass two
houses. in such circumstances.
but never a third.
You murdered my
brother in cold blood!
It's not true!
We argued about some disputed
land. He pulled out a knife!
You wanted that
land for yourself!
You're a liar and a coward.
Who says I'm a
coward? I'm not a coward.
Silence!
As the normal procedures
were not followed.
this killing cannot
be atoned for
by compensating
the victim's family.
Murder is a dishonorable
deed amongst our people.
Carried out in secret.
unacknowledged.
and likely to give rise to
a series of revenge killings
that would involve
your own family.
Lord. you knew about that land.
You knew I had a
claim to it... Enough!
I ask you to look
to the accused.
If you think that he is guilty.
raise your arms.
The decision must be unanimous.
Eric Trygvasson.
you have been
found guilty of murder.
Yes! MAN 2: Justice!
How do you wish to die?
By beheading. Lord.
Your wish is granted. You
shall be executed tomorrow.
After which we shall feast and
talk about the summer raids.
You have to.
Why is he smiling. Father?
He wants to die
well. without fear.
to atone for his sins.
You must watch. for his sake.
It's his only hope
of reaching Valhalla.
Feed him to your pigs!
And I curse him.
May he never enter Valhalla.
May he never
feast with the gods.
Why did he do that?
He should not have done that.
Someone told me he
wanted that land for himself.
and he knew Trygvasson
had the best claim to it.
but refused to sell it.
You hear that. boy? This is
how things are done around here.
Olaf. son of Ingolf.
Bjorn. son of Ragnar.
may you accept this
gift of salt and earth
to remind yourself that you
belong to both the land and the sea.
These arm rings bind you in
loyalty to me. your lord. your chieftain.
Any oath that you swear on these
rings must be honored and kept.
Do you understand
and swear to this?
Yes. Lord. Yes. Lord.
And do you freely give your fealty
to me. your lord. your chieftain?
Yes. Lord. Yes. Lord.
Good. You may
put on the arm rings.
Come here.
Let us feast!
My Lord.
we all want to feast.
but we also want to know where
we will be raiding this summer.
Can't it wait. Ragnar?
No. Tell us.
We want to know.
We have a right to know.
Very well.
We will raid east again. to
the eastlands and into Russia.
Every year
we go to the same places!
But there is an alternative.
if you choose.
Yes. yes. Choice. yes.
I have heard of these
rumors. these stories.
That if we travel west. that
we will somehow reach a land
that is rich and plentiful.
But I tell you that I will not
risk my ships or my reputation
on such a deluded fantasy.
They are my ships.
I pay for them.
And they go where
I tell them to go.
Now that's the
end of the matter.
Let's feast!
Let me see!
It's a fine ring.
Ragnar Lothbrok.
Earl Haraldson wants to
speak with you in private.
Stay with your uncle.
Ragnar Lothbrok.
Sit down.
Are you hungry?
Yes. Lord.
You want to feast in my hall?
You want to sail in my ships?
Anything else you want from me?
Lord...
You keep talking about the west.
What do you know of it? Hmm?
Why are you so certain
that it's a land of great riches?
I can't be sure.
But I believe that...
I don't care what you believe.
You insulted me out there.
and not for the first time.
but. believe me.
it will be the last.
Who told you you could go?
You are a farmer.
You should be
content with your lot.
Farms are few and
in great demand.
and there are many people here
who would like to
possess your land.
Do you understand
what I'm saying?
I understand.
Then don't ever stick
your nose in my face again.
I don't trust him. Watch him.
Where are they?
Where are my sons?
You said you'd found them.
Where are we going
now? I'm so tired.
To talk to the gods.
It's what we do.
Why don't you
come in? I'm waiting.
Sit.
What do you want?
I want to know what
the gods have in store.
For you. or for the boy?
I'm more interested in myself.
The gods desire you to
have a great future. I see that.
But they can withdraw
their goodwill at any time.
To have this great future.
must I challenge the law?
You must convince the
gods to alter the runes
so they work in your favor.
But the laws of men
are far below the workings
and shapings of the gods.
So I should take the laws of men
into my own hands?
Answer me.
You already have your answer.
No. I don't.
Well. then go and
ask the gods yourself.
What are you afraid of?
Wait outside.
All right.
You haven't helped
me at all. ancient one.
Perhaps you asked
the wrong questions.
We have someone
special to visit.
His name is Floki.
"Floki"?
Like Loki. the god?
Yes. only different.
How is he different?
He's not a god.
Why didn't he come to the thing?
Because...
Because he's shy.
Floki. this is my son. Bjorn.
Hello. How are you?
Well. Thank you. sir.
Let me see.
You have your father's eyes
unfortunately.
Why unfortunately?
It means he will be like you.
and therefore he will
want to do better than you.
and you will hate him for it.
How can you tell that by
just looking at my face?
It's the same with trees.
I can tell which trees will make
the best planks just
by looking at them.
I can look inside the tree.
Floki is a boat-builder.
Among other things.
This is one.
Inside this tree are two
almost perfect planks.
They will bend. then curve.
like a woman's body
from the thighs to the back.
When I split this
tree. I will find them.
You can see that?
Do you think I'm joking?
I joke about many
things. son of Ragnar.
but never about ship-building.
Do you imagine ships
are just dead things?
So. what about our boat?
It will be lighter and
carry a bigger sail.
The construction is different.
It's built with a
strong central plank.
The two strakes
above it are nailed
directly onto the
knees of the frame.
But the ones below... Look!
Are cleated and lashed
onto the frames. not nailed.
so they can move in
relation to each other.
This means the boat won't butt
against the waves like a goat.
but move over
them like a ripple.
The hull is deeper. How
will my men set their oars?
I will cut them into
the sheerstrakes.
and the ports can be closed
when the boat is at sea.
And you think it could
handle long sea voyages?
That's why I'm building it.
But will it be strong enough?
We won't know that until we try.
For the anchor.
It's all I have left from
last summer's raids.
Don't worry.
We'll soon be as
rich as dwarves!
I missed you.
Did anything happen
while we were away?
No.
Did you miss me?
I ached with love longing.
My belly was empty of laughter.
Is that what you want? Hmm?
You want me to make you laugh?
I don't want to laugh now.
I want to ride you.
like a bull.
Like a wild bull.
Hello. young Bjorn.
Hello. Rollo.
Where are your parents?
They are having sex.
Well...
I guess we'll have to wait.
So. Gyda.
is your mother teaching
you how to use a shield?
Yes. I know how to use a shield.
Your mother was a
famous shield-maiden.
Was?
Is a famous shield-maiden.
Come on. children. to bed.
- Do I have to?
Let's leave the men.
But I'm a man. I have a ring.
Let him stay awhile.
To bed!
Say good night.
Good night. my children.
- Good night.
Good night. Good night.
Hey!
Good night. Father.
Tell me your news.
What about the boat?
It's nearly ready.
I won't go under your command.
I won't go unless
we're all equal.
We are brothers.
You and I will always be equal.
Then we must find a crew.
Not many men will go against
the wishes of Haraldson.
Many will be afraid.
Some may even go
to him and betray us.
I must go piss.
Yesterday. I was with
a girl from the town.
Thank you.
A good-looking girl. too.
But when she
shouted out in pleasure.
I didn't see her face.
I saw yours.
Lagertha...
Don't talk like that.
Why not?
I think about you all the time.
That's too bad.
Don't insult me. shield-maiden.
No.
I would never insult you.
You're too great a warrior.
but perhaps not so great a man.
I saw something.
What did you see?
A sign.
It made me certain
we're doing the right thing.
Good night. brother.
Set the sail.
Floki! The sail!
She'll sink.
No. she bloody won't.
I shouldn't have pretended
to build such a boat.
It's beyond my
humble capabilities.
I'll set the sail.
I'm sorry. Ragnar.
I've wasted all your
money. It was all a joke.
Shut up. man.
Ha!
Now it runs on its cool keel.
It's beautiful.
Why didn't you believe
me? I told you I could do it!
Now it's all up to
you. Ragnar Lothbrok.